A Register of the Charles Shipman papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles Shipman papers
1895-1986
2005C62
Shipman, Charles
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (2.59 Linear feet)
Contains correspondence, memoirs, meeting minutes, plays, clippings, notes, and photographs relating to the life of Charles Shipman. Shipman was active in anti-war, anti-imperialist, and communist groups in the United States. He was also a delegate to the second and sixth Communist International congresses, and was a communist leader in Mexico under the name Manuel Gomez.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
Access to sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2005
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1895 August 10 Born Charles Francis Phillips in New York City
1913-1914 Attends Columbia University Extension classes
1914-1917 Attends Columbia School of Journalism
1915 December Participates in Ford Peace Expedition as Observer
1917 Organizing Secretary of the Collegiate Anti-Militarism League
1918 March Travels to Mexico to begin work for Communist Party
1919 Travels to Spain with Communist agent Mikhail Markovich Borodin under the name Jesus Ramirez
1920 Delegate to the 2nd Communist International Congress Returns to Mexico, working under the name Manuel Gomez
1921 Returns to United States, settling in Chicago
1923-1928 Secretary, All-America Anti-Imperialist League
1927 Moves to New York City
1928 Delegate to the 6th Communist International Congress
1930-1934 Works as journalist and editor at several newspapers, including the Wall Street News, Wall Street Journal, and New York Post
1937-1948 Works at Standard and Poor's
Scope and Contents note
Contains correspondence, memoirs, meeting minutes, plays, clippings, notes, and photographs relating to the life of Charles Shipman. Shipman was active in anti-war, anti-imperialist, and communist groups in the United States. He was also a delegate to the second and sixth Communist International congresses, and was a communist leader in Mexico under the name Manuel Gomez. The Subject files document this activity. Shipman's life is chronicled in his memoirs, which are found in the Writings series along with plays Shipman translated and adapted from Spanish. The Photographs series is composed of portraits of Shipman and prints depicting meetings, family, and friends.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is arranged in three series: Subject files, 1895-1986; Writings, 1960-1971; and Photographs, 1915-1982.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
All-America Anti-Imperialist League.; Communist International.; Anti-imperialist movements.; Communism--Mexico.; Communism--United States.; Peace movements.
Collection Contents
- Subject file, 1895-1986; 0.4 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Consists of correspondence, meeting minutes, clippings, and notes related to Shipman's life and work with anti-war, anti-imperialist, and communist groups in the United States and Mexico.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
  - All-America Anti-Imperialist League, 1920-1930, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
  - American Communist Party, 1923-1982 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Biographical file, 1928-1985 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Ford expedition, 1915-1966 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - New Masses, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Passports, 1915-1975 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    Includes passports for Charles Shipman and his wife Sylvia Feningston
  - Peace meeting, 1895 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Personalities and friends, 1965-1984 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Pic and Carlota, 1945-1983 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Pre-Mexico data (correspondence), 1917-1918, 1966 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Includes letters regarding Shipman's decision to be a conscientious objector during World War I.
  - Redding, Connecticut, 1941-1985 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    Includes Ah Catalina! programs
  - Russia and the Comintern, 1967-1984 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Work-related clippings, 1956-1986 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Workers Monthly, 1923-1925 (Box-folder 1: 15)
- Writings, 1960-1971; 0.6 Linear feet (Box 2-3)
  Contains an autobiographical transcript, Shipman's memoirs, and plays adapted and translated from Spanish.
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Biographical typescript (uncorrected), undated (Box-folder 2: 1-4)
  - Natural Enough: An Autobiography, undated (Box-folder 2: 5-9)
  - The Lady from Havana, 1960 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Papa by a Landslide, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Gasoline for Mamma, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Ah Catalina!, 1964, 1971 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - "From Mexico to Moscow," Survey: A Journal of Soviet and Eastern Studies, v. 55, 1965 April (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Encounter in a Doctor's Waiting Room, 1970 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Photographs, 1915-1982; 1.55 Linear feet (Box 3-4)
  Composed of images of Shipman himself, family, friends, communist meetings, and play rehearsals.
  Arranged in chronological order by group.
  - Portraits of Charles Shipman, undated (Box 4)
  - Meetings and groups, 1915-1972 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    Includes images of communist meetings.
  - Shipman family and friends, 1919-1972 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - "Haitian Patriotic Union banquet for Mr. Manuel Gomez,", 1928 September 30 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous snapshots, 1947-1982 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Ah Catalina! rehearsals, 1964 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - International Summer School, University of Cambridge, 1975 (Box 4)